Awesome, you guys are here today.
Hi, we have a lot of my friend Nick.
Nick, as well as Amory, and I've joined us from Crossroads Community Church just down
the street.
A couple, about a year and a month ago, I felt burdened to, I've been here for about
a year, and didn't have many relationships with all the churches in the area, and I felt
like that was not a great thing.
And so I just, like, saw the 12th call when you needed many churches, and I was like,
hey, we need to buy all the lunches or something.
And so out of that, I was going to have a little monthly prayer lunch, but what happened
is Nick and Bobby showed up some crossroads for our first prayer lunch, and I quickly realized
that, like, they had been doing the, like, getting together with all the pastors things
for far longer than I had even, like, thought about it.
Like, continuing as, like, a person of peace when it comes to churches working together
with other churches, and so that's one reason I wanted to have Nick here is just to show
our values as a church that we are a kingdom people.
The kingdom of God is far greater than what happens in all four walls, but there's churches
all over our community right now preaching the gospel of English, seeking to go to his kingdom,
and we want to partner with what kind of community has to be.
The second reason is we're in this series called Resurrection Rumors, and today we're going
to look at the Ascension Encounter, and in church history, today is Ascension Sunday.
And Nick is a student of church history and a student of the church calendar, and so I just thought
he would have great words for us to share.
So I invite Nick to come with us, and we pray for him, for us, and yeah, it'll be great.
Father, we are so grateful for your word, that it's unchanging and never failing, that it
doesn't return void, that we pray for your heart's guilt to be present and active in this
way.
We believe that he is present and used to be studied and prepared this message, and we believe
that you will take that of faithfulness from any world, and the plant seeds, water seeds,
and have a seeds this morning to apply for him to the other world.
Father, Isaac is a servant.
Thank you for his faithfulness to our community, and so it's helpful in his other role that does
that we're ready to thank you for his own work of community.
Is it foreign to a deal better?
Is it all?
Awesome.
Well, thank you.
I'm very honored to be with you this morning, and I always found it a great honor when I get
to hear the word, but even more so in my own family.
It's not too often I get an invite to a hometown church, and it's not that I feel like Jesus
will cross, but that's nice in his hometown, but, you know, we all have some of our things
that we're doing as local churches, and so I really do just want to honor Ryan and honor
you as Jesus for just the acumenical things that you're doing in the community.
I saw some of you at Recessant Collective last week, and I thought that was amazing,
the relationship that you've been developing, that I've been developing, first with Ryan
and some others, and just actually some in this room that we used to go to church with
Jenny and Ted, Jenny and Ted, and then a few others that go here.
I don't see them in here, I have to give them my high time, so I'm not telling you enough
when I come to this school.
So it's an honor to be here, very grateful to get to share the word of you this morning.
Kind of some, like, opening thoughts in your prayer this morning.
I was sitting in a chair by our window.
We normally have a very noisy street in the old town, and this morning, though, it was
very peaceful.
Normally, Sundays are.
Saturdays could be a little bit more loud, but this morning, just sitting there listening
to some birds of purple, and just praying quietly, just allowing the spirit to just move and
speak, because I was praying for, you know, all of you this morning on what to, on just, you know,
maybe there's something else that the Lord might have to you this morning.
And so, I felt like it was John 6.31 looking into my mind.
I'm sorry.
It was 6.31 came to me, and I was like, maybe it's an address, but no, you know, I looked
at John, and it was John 6.31, and Jesus is sharing with the disciples about manna that
came from heaven that was a gift from the Father, not from Moses.
And so, we looked for leaders to feed us, but it's really the Heavenly Father is the one
that gives us the bread of life.
And so, as we go into what I'm going to share this morning, I want you to receive this morning
as the Father would be giving you testimony.
And then, at the end, I'm absolutely loving that we're going to culminate today with coming
together at the Lord's table.
So, just to open these thoughts as I, before I dig into my, what I just said this morning,
I had three things kind of, like, really boiled to the surface as I was getting through all
of this, and one of them was, the more you learn, the less you realize you know.
And anybody who's, you know, been around for any period of time, you know that there's,
you learn something new all the time when you thought you had it down.
Something comes around and says you may be a different way.
And then, the second is that the gospel needs to be the centrality in our teaching.
It needs to be how we live our life.
So, don't let you be living one way in church on Sunday and in another way when you go to
the grocery store after we leave here today.
And then lastly, that the essential of Christ is the most important theology or doctrine that
is overlooked, lumped into all these old times, completely ignored in the church.
And we're going to dig into that a little bit more.
And it's overlooked in most churches in the West because Pentecost has been given sort of
a higher value.
And Pentecost has a high value.
This does not need to mention next Sunday, which is Pentecost Sunday, but the essential Sunday
needs to be viewed as itself within a larger framework of Christ's work.
Garrett Dawson, Garrett Dawson, oh my goodness, where's his name?
He wrote a book, Scott Garrett Dawson wrote a book, and in the end he called it,
the continual incarnation of Jesus.
Jesus didn't just was born into Mary, it was conceived into Mary, born, lived, died, resurrected,
ascended in the seat of the right hand of the Father.
It's one long, continuing thing, and then we're going to hopefully be able to really hammer
on the point that it's not over.
Jesus is born very much alive in his bodily and spiritual form at the right hand of the
Father.
And you don't pay attention to the news, they'll tell you that the world's going to down the
toilet because Christ wins in the end.
Jesus is still alive.
He's not dead.
Amen?
All right, so here we go, let's jump into this.
So today we're going to be exploring the ascension, how the ascension is viewed historically.
Also, we're going to look at some foreshadowing and even pathetically synopsis in the Old
Testament that will give us a window to look through as what was to come.
We are also going to be looking at two very real, but seemingly different, but closer than some
of us, we're going to be looking at the scene and the unseen realms.
Or a student's human, who is a professor at Asbury University, Kentucky, calls it the
"seen and unseen real" because we're both very real.
This one of them seems a little more real because I can touch the scenes of it.
But yet, this is only my human experience that I'm using them in.
The unseen realm, we don't see it without an answer to us, but we have examples throughout
the Old Testament where you have men and women who both have seen into the spiritual realm.
So we're going to dig in.
Let's roll up our sleeves.
I know I don't have any, but I'm going to roll these up anyways.
And we're going to read Acts 1:7-11, and I'll be in the New American Standard Version.
He says, "It is not for you to know the times and epochs which the Father has fixed with
his own authority, but you will receive power when the Holy Spirit is come upon you, and
you shall be my witnesses between Jerusalem, and all of Judea, and Samaria, and even to
the remotest parts of the earth."
And then after he had said these things, he was lifted up, and while they were looking at
the sun, and a cloud received him out of their sight, and as they were gazing at the sky
while he was going, behold, two men in white clothing stood beside them.
And they also said, "Men of Galilee, wide these things looking into the sky, this Jesus,
who has been taken from you to heaven, will come in the same way, just as you have watched
him go into heaven."
When writing on the ascension, N.C. Wright says this, "If Christ, after his resurrection,
ascended into the heavenly realm and took his feet at the right human side of where he
remained..."
Oh, let me jump.
I jump.
Hold on.
Err.
Back up.
Pay attention to him.
When writing on the ascension, N.C. Wright says about C.S. Lewis' Narnia stories, which most
of you are very familiar with you use as a beautiful literary example of two worlds that can relate
to each other in their life, heaven and earth, together.
The dwelling place of God, which is heaven, and then earth, which is where the image days
are there is that God created dwell.
So if you just were ascension allowed, some of you might be asking, "What does this mean?"
So what is ascension, and why is it important?
This is my first point.
In its most fantastic name, the ascension is this.
Christ, after his resurrection, ascended into the heavenly realm and took his feet at
the right hand of the Father, where he remains today.
To help define ascension a little bit more, we need to make a brief distinction between
two things.
We need to define, we need to look at resurrection, and we need to look at ascension, because they're
two very different things.
We have many biblical examples throughout the Bible of resurrection.
We have examples in the Old Testament, where Elijah and Elijah both prayed, and somebody
was resurrected from the dead.
In the New Testament, we have Lazarus, we have Jesus' daughter, and of course we have most
notably our Savior Christ.
He was raised from the dead.
Now, I'm going to say something that's maybe a little bit spicy, but it's okay, because we're
going to explain it.
So, resurrection, or revising from the dead, is something man and God can do.
Modern medicine has advanced to the place where, right now, if anybody had a heart attack
that went on the ground, somebody might be trained in CPR in this room, and if you have
heartiness stopped, you're technically dead, and we could revive you and come back.
That's like resurrection.
You know, so that's something that man and God can do.
God raised Jesus from the dead.
When Elijah and Elijah both prayed for somebody, God is the one that raised him from the dead.
They didn't give anything to God, but today we came.
Now, what makes ascension different?
This is only something God can do.
Let's go back to Elijah.
2 Kings 2:11 gives us a story of Elijah being taken up in heaven.
And it reads:
"The words were going along and talking before there appeared, it's tearing a fire, and forces
of fire which separated the two of them, which is Elijah and Eden Elijah.
And Elijah went up into a world ring into heaven."
The word "world ring" is used 16 times in the Old Testament, and each of them is used
as God communicating something or an action of something that is going to happen.
And this is an action that God is doing.
God caused Elijah to be raised up in a world ring taken up in heaven.
It's not something Elijah could do.
Very important distinction.
This is why the ascension is so important, because only God has the ability and the opponent.
For somebody to ascend.
And then somebody, I mean, Elijah did it, but it's really a bad answer.
Well, one other thing before we move on, because some of you might be wondering,
there's two stories of ascension in the New Testament.
One is in Luke chapter 24, and one of them is in Acts.
We're going to be focusing on the Acts part here,
because in Luke, he's really finishing his narrative,
and so he doesn't really give a lot of context on what he's doing.
And so with Acts, you get context, you get a little bit more breadth,
and he's raised out in context of also the succession of events of time,
so we get a little bit more in that verse, and that's why we're not going to use it.
So let's jump into, we're going to talk about the common historical view.
I mean, Luke, a priest friend of mine said that the ascension was, at one point, the third most important day in the church family.
The first being resurrection.
My thought of view on this is that over time, we've seen changes mainly from a shift from historical understanding to what is called modernity,
which is taking over in the western church.
We do not have time to find untested identity.
You're going to have to Google that when undone.
Because that would, we're going to, we, Ryan would have to start a small group to help you unpack a little bit more what,
what modernity is.
But as I mentioned this in the beginning of the day of the season,
that the ascension gets swallowed up in the Easter and resurrected minerals,
and it gets overshadowed by penetrates.
And one of these are deeply important that we need to see them as separate things but in a larger content.
From a high-level age, we just make it like a neat point, but from a perspective of the early church Scripture,
and the history of the formation of church doctrine, the ascension is a vital part in remembrance and celebration in the life of Christ.
We see this in church history in the Apostles' Creed.
Is anybody familiar with the Apostles' Creed?
Some of us probably are.
I'm not going to read the whole thing, I'm just going to read a part of it.
And it reads like this.
The Apostles' Creed says,
I believe in God's Father, the Almighty, the creator of heaven and earth.
I believe in Jesus Christ, his only Son of our Lord, who was conceived by the Holy Spirit,
born of the Virgin Mary, suffered from the Prince of Pilate, was crucified, was died in his birth.
He descended into the dead, and then on the third day he raised again,
he ascended into heaven, where he is seated at the right hand of the Son of God.
He's got his own place inside one of the most important church documents in the formation of the church.
Since the third and fourth century, this has been used to explain the life of Christ in a very concise manner that the whole church would say,
"This is the story of Jesus."
St. Jerome, in his commentary, Ryan then makes a joke and I make this joke all the time.
I'm going to quote a lot of people that are no longer living.
I really love to dig into church history and quote names that some of you might not be familiar with,
but this is part of our church history and breadth of Christianity.
St. Jerome says this in his commentary about all about Luke.
He says that the writer, referring to Luke, says,
"The actual risk is so that the exalted Christ is beyond the limitation of such fears,
fears leading to heavenlies,
that his power and act of presence extends to all the universe."
There's something very important that the early church worked through when they were talking about the Ascension,
when they were figuring out what was he doing?
What did he do?
How did all of these things kind of fit into place?
Let's move on to the Old Testament and talk about foreshadowing and prophecy.
Why am I using the term foreshadowing in a parenthesis?
Foreshadowing is important because there's similarities in stories that give us examples of something that may happen.
Or in retrospect, you can look back and you can see that it gives us the grace of something that's coming in the future.
Foreshadowing is necessarily storytelling, but it's not necessarily prophecy.
It's different.
Some of you here are writers in here who are English majors will know what I'm talking about.
I'm not an English major, so if I've said anything incorrectly, you know what I'm doing later.
Processing is a prediction of something that is to come.
Some things that are processing need to be viewed very importantly and put in a higher place.
Foreshadowing is about storytelling.
So let's first revisit something that has been mentioned about Elijah being taken up in heaven.
I'm going to read first 2 Kings 2, 11 through 13 again.
And he says,
As they were going along and talking, behold, there appeared, I carried a fire and forces of fire that separated the two of them.
And Elijah went up on a road in heaven.
And Elijah saw it and cried out,
My father, my father, my father.
The spirits of Israel and his horsemen.
Followed Elijah in the morning.
Then he took a hold of his own clothes and tore them into two pieces.
Then he took up the mantle of Elijah that fell from him and returned and he was spilled by the banks of the Jordan.
We see foreshadowing in the ascension in Pentecost here.
What do I mean by that?
The foreshadowing of the ascension of Elijah ascending by the power of God, not man.
But then we also see a foreshadowing of Pentecost with the mantle of Elijah falling and then Elijah picking it up.
And now he has a double portion.
That's a foreshadowing of the Holy Spirit coming at the time of Pentecost and showing his planes of fire on men and women.
But at that point, so now they have an extra spirit with them.
Foreshadowing is very important.
Elijah ascended by the power of God, not his own.
And his spirit descended on Elijah and he received a double portion.
This is a beautiful picture of the church calendar.
Of the events of this time.
Of the ascension and his influence.
Let's move on to Moses.
This is a foreshadowing and prophecy.
Moses ascended up to the mountain to receive the law from God and bring God's prophetic voice down to the people of Israel.
And then I know we have an example in Exodus 24 where Joshua goes with Moses up to the mountain.
He was sitting outside the camp.
But Moses was the one who would bring down the law.
Moses was the one who needs the voice of God.
Moses was the one who had to cover his face from being in the presence of God.
And he was so bright that Israel said, I can't look at you.
You need to cover your face.
Moses also said in Deuteronomy 1815, this is the prophecy piece.
Moses writes, "The Lord will rise up a prophet like me among you."
So, foreshadowing, Moses going up a mountain.
Prophecy.
Moses saying there is another one that would be coming like me speaking to Jesus.
One more example of foreshadowing.
I actually love this.
I'm not sure if you, if anybody's, you know, I still believe that there's a small group like Corey's reading about a book.
So, this is for Corey, but he's not here today.
So, please give him a hard time when you see a minute.
So, this is the foreshadowing of Moses and the exodus of God's people out of the bondage of slavery in Egypt.
There's a foreshadowing of Jesus leading us out of the bondage of slavery in Egypt.
Because when Jesus walked in, rode in on a donkey at the time of Passover during Israel's calendar,
he died rose and died rose again during the time of Passover.
Not during the time of the coming, which is very anointing.
So, it's a foreshadowing of Jesus leading what some call a new exodus.
So, it's a foreshadowing of what Jesus is going to do, not prophecy.
Very important to make the decision.
And the last one is Psalm 110, where David says,
"The Lord said to my Lord, sit at my right hand until I make you enemies of such glory."
The first three chapters.
Elijah was a foreshadowing of the offense in the coming of us.
Moses was a foreshadowing and prophecy of what was to come.
And he's Psalm 110's prophecy.
Very important that we can get a whole, full breadth of Scripture in theology.
We're going to move into what I'm calling the convergence of two spaces and two spheres.
But Tim Mackey and the Bible Project, some of you may be familiar with their work.
He has one of the best explanations of heaven and earth converging.
The beautiful illustrations share how God's space, heaven, and man's space, earth,
come together in different ways throughout Scripture.
I highly recommend it.
If you don't have time to watch one of their videos,
it would probably be way better watching a cartoon with him explaining than me telling you to you right now.
So, let's look at a few things.
First, we're going to look at even.
And we're going to see man and God sharing the same space.
In Genesis 3:8, it says,
"They heard the sound of the Lord walking in the garden in the four of the day,
and man and his wife hid themselves from the price of the Lord among the trees."
God was walking in the space that man was.
They shared the same space.
Albeit, this is where his story goes terribly wrong.
But, please start to Jesus.
Second, we're going to look at the tabernacle and the temple.
Each of these were places where the presence of God dwelt,
yet many did not have unfettered access to it.
There was divine worship.
There was a personality that many had to do to interact with God in this space.
And there also had to be shed blood.
There had to be the blood of a goat or a bull or a bird.
There had to be shed blood so that the priest was able to enter into the Holy of Holies.
And that's where the presence of God dwelt.
He couldn't just come and go outside of them.
There's also an example in David's story where they go to move the Ark of the Covenant,
and the priests just do it flippantly, and somebody dies because they touch him.
The presence of God, God was revealing to them the intentionality in how he used to approach him.
Don't just do it.
It's all those selfish ambitions.
Next, we're going to look at Jesus, the resurrection, ascension, and the new exodus.
Jesus' journey entered Jerusalem began the most important journey any human had ever taken.
And to this day, it still hasn't.
Nobody will ever take a journey that many others have deeply driven.
Jesus entered the city limits of Jerusalem on the back of the donkey of the Passover celebration
that the Jewish people celebrated every year, celebrating their liberation from slavery in Egypt.
Next, Jesus became the Passover lamb.
His blood from the crucifixion became the last, final, and dare I say,
most important sacrifice that's ever taken place in the history of the world.
On the third day, he rose from the dead in a very real sense and a very real body.
A body that would speak with, interact with, and even give one apostle the opportunity to stick his finger in the wound.
And then we deal with Thomas, as most of our Bibles say, God and Thomas, above that first Scripture.
Why do we say God and Thomas?
Because he got to experience the very flesh of the risen Lord.
I'm not going to punch Thomas.
It's okay to have examples of something that happened, yet in history you've just Thomas a hard time
because you asked for Jesus to do something a little bit more and it's okay.
When we come to the ascension or convergence of two spaces.
Remember how I started with C.S. Lewis and the Narnia stories.
You have two spaces that come together in a wardrobe where two new worlds can kind of go back and forth between these two spaces.
And you hear me clearly, I'm not saying that we can go back and forth between heaven and earth like the wardrobe in Narnia, okay?
I just don't send Ryan an email this week stating that that's what this guy said.
No, that's not what I'm saying.
What I'm saying is that we are left, that the ascension is the things of our faith.
That the story of Narnia reveals how heaven and earth can come together and that place converges in Jesus.
That place comes together in the man and the God who was and is our Savior Jesus.
Jesus is the things of our faith in the convergence of God in man.
He affirms in his masterpiece, space, time, and resurrection.
He says this about the ascension.
The ascension means that we cannot know God by transcending space and time by leaping beyond our own limits of earth,
but by encountering God and his saving work within our space and time, with our actual physical existence.
Each one of us in this room, those who are online, those who are at our church, those who are at churches across the world,
and those who are at work right now, those who are sitting at home because they don't feel well,
in their very real existence on this earth, they encounter God by faith saving work, not by money, and not by yours.
Matthew 6 and Luke 11, clearly our Father, I'm sorry, I'm Catholic and orthodox up reading.
You might know it as the word prayer.
It says this in a very specific meaning that we're going to say we need to pull something out of this.
Our Father, who is in heaven, hallowed be thy name.
Your kingdom come, your will be done, on earth as it is in heaven.
Give us this day our daily bread, and forgive us our debt.
As we also forgive our debtors, sorry, I was praying with you.
Why am I reading between both of these?
Focus up here, bud.
Do not read us into temptation, but deliver us from evil.
For yours is the kingdom and the power and glory forever. Amen.
On earth as it is in heaven is only possible because Christ ascended.
If Christ did not ascend to be seated right on the Father, there's no reason for us to be seated here today.
That's the things of our faith, the convergence for man and God come together.
1 Timothy 2.5 says,
For there is one God, one mediator, also between God and man, the man, Jesus Christ.
That is our hope.
That is our faith.
It's in this man who did something, who does something, who is very active and alive today.
In the obvious child of this library, many names, chapter titled, "Crescent Risenness," which is one of my favorite chapters of any book I've ever read.
He hears the story of G.K. Chesterton, a 20th century writer, who quite possibly might be the greatest writer that none of us have ever read.
C.S. Lewis read G.K. Chesterton, and that's what brought him to Christ.
He says this, in the most eloquent way, in very, very short.
He's standing on the street corner, and the journalist comes to him and says, "You're a recent convert to Christianity.
What would you say if Jesus was standing right here with us?"
And he says, "Oh, but he is."
C.S. Lewis remains present and see the brave human father, or as I've mentioned before from Mr. Dawson in his book, "Jesus is Fringles."
He says the space between us and Jesus is collapsed by the Holy Spirit.
Therefore, there is no distance too wide or too far for God to interact to us in our human existence.
Once again, we are reminded by the fact that it's not by our power.
It is by God's might that he came to us.
It is not by something I have to do.
I learned that very intentionally, or very, like, not like I sought this out.
This is it.
God interrupted my life 14 years ago on the floor of a pizza shop in Stephen City.
When my license ever came, he invaded my space.
He revered himself to me as Father, and Holy Spirit just came in like a world running my life.
Now, I wasn't ascended into heaven.
This is me getting weird enough.
If God invaded me, I didn't go to him.
Just like anybody in this room, there's no line in everybody in the history of the world.
God invades us.
The Holy Spirit has come for us.
It explains this in John 16, 5 through 15.
A lot of Scripture, and I'm trying to wrap up on him.
I don't want to get two soldiers.
I don't want you guys to beat up one and two once.
I'm trying to nail this just right.
John 16, 1 through 5 says,
"But now I am going to him who sent me.
And none of you ask, where are you going?
But because you have said these things,
because I have said these things to you, sorrow has filled your heart.
I will tell you the truth.
And if you're advantage, then I go away.
For if I do not go away, the helper will not come to you.
But if I go away, I will send him to you.
And he, when he comes, will convict the world concerning sin."
Is that the notion that you will convict the world?
Let's not go to the next thing unless someone convict the world.
I will send you righteousness and judgment concerning sin because they do not believe in me.
I will send you righteousness because I go to the Father and you no longer see me.
I will send you judgment because the ruler of this world has been judged.
I have many more things to say to you, but you cannot bear than me.
But when he, the Spirit of his comes, he will guide you and ask you.
He will not speak on his own initiative, but when he hears, he will speak.
He will disclose to you what is to come.
He will glorify me, for he will be take of mine and will disclose to me.
All things that the Father has are mine.
Therefore I said that he takes of mine, will disclose to you.
Jesus, the convergence point of heaven and earth, with Holy Spirit floating between these two spheres.
Jesus had to go.
Jesus had to ascend.
For that presence of Jesus to be able to be all over the world and not just with his disciples.
Once we could ascend so the Spirit could come so that we all have a helper.
And not just the select few of people.
I started with two verses that I have in touch on you.
Verses 7 and 8 in Acts 1.
And it says this:
It is not for you to know the times and e-punks, which the Father has fixed by his own authority,
that you will receive power when the Holy Spirit has come upon you, and you can be my witnesses.
Make note of this:
In Jerusalem, in Judea, all of Samaria, until the remotest parts of the earth.
As Jesus is about to move on the next step of his own authority.
As Jesus is about to move on the next step of his own covenant, he says one last important diploma.
For those who refuse his writings.
And that's for us to serve in 2000, such as his writings.
He says in Jerusalem, in Judea, in all of Samaria, in the remotest parts of the earth.
He begins with Jerusalem.
Because he says this speaks to the Jewish people, the law, the temple, even the religious system.
And some of us today, most of us will pray that that religious system is corrupted.
The first name speaks to Judah.
And this speaks to the division within Israel.
Because at one point, Israel had a divided kingdom, only two kings.
One is in Jerusalem, and one is in Judea.
This brings Israel back together.
Three is familiar.
And this speaks to the Gentiles, which would be us,
or those who mixed with the Jews, who weren't technically full-blood youth.
This brings everyone under the kingdom of God.
And then this fourth one is rather strange.
Because it says some of the translations might say furtherest.
I mean, I'm not supposed to be rightest.
It's all the same word.
So the first three spoke of people, nations, and geography.
But the last word speaks for geography and time.
What do I mean by that?
Let's look a little closer.
This word is used fifty-three times in the New Testament.
And each time is used in the form of awareness and, or in this case, earthness or remoteness.
I'll do my best to pronounce this Greek word.
I'm not a Greek scholar.
My friend in the bank is taking Greek.
You can probably refer to it much better than me.
It's eschatology.
Which is the root word where you get the theology term eschatology.
Which means the theology of end times.
And what I'm about to say to you is not an Orthodox approach or the historical church view.
But this is what I'm going to surmise out of this.
I'm going to submit this to you this morning.
Considering how this word is used and denoted as the last of something of both time and place.
Jesus' call to his listeners and for us today is a call to ask them.
To first be witnesses in Jerusalem for the Jews.
To be witnesses in their local aid.
And then to be witnesses in Judea.
To bring together the people of God once again.
And then to be witnesses in Samaria when you're calling the Gentiles into the faith.
For the ones who were once said that you can not worship in Jerusalem.
Now you can come to the very presence of God.
And then he speaks to his future not just geographical things.
But he's saying go share the gospel to the furthest parts of the earth.
And to the end of the earth.
Not just let's get to the last tribe.
And then now that everybody's had the Bible the earth is going to explode.
That's not what I'm saying.
That everywhere on this whole planet we need to be teaching the gospel.
Hearing the word until the end.
And we don't know when that end is.
Don't try to do the math.
Because everybody that has in the class hasn't gotten it right.
Don't worry about doing the math.
Worry about doing the gospel.
Worry about sharing the good news of Jesus.
Worry about who's ascended and actually don't worry that you're ascended.
But live your life as you are sharing the gospel in everything that we do.
I'm enjoying this.
The word is specific.
You need to live which is sharing.
Right now I get an opportunity to say locally I serve at Crossroads.
But I have another role with our church organization that's a part of us called Dove.
Where I'm the youth director for the USA.
Where I get to travel to churches and tour into young people.
But there's a summer we do a CMT in evangelistic missions training.
Where for eight days we take like 150 youth and leaders and we go to writing Pennsylvania for the sake of the gospel.
If I'm not reading the gospel in every day, what am I doing?
What's the point of it?
This is what I believe that the call is.
The call is usually saying unite.
Come together.
For the sake of one thing, through the gospel.
And not just for now, but until the end of time.
And we don't know when that is.
So therefore, don't stop.
I know we get tired.
I know that we grow weary.
And we know that life is tough and we have wonderful church and peace.
Ronnie says awesome things that's going on at campus community church.
And we share that, you share that in this community of this part of Winchester.
You have a call for this part of Winchester.
Y'all, so I know a little bit of the two churches merging together.
That's a convergence of two bodies coming together for the sake of one thing.
For bringing the body of Christ together for the sake of the gospel and nothing else.
Because I'm not going to come to church on Sunday morning if it's not for the sake of the gospel.
What's the point?
If I want to listen to good music, I can put it in an earbud and go on a walk and turn on radio at the house.
And we intentionally come because we worship together.
We sing praises to the one who is worthy of it all for the sake of the gospel.
And then, I'm going to invite somebody to come up and pray.
And I know that we're going to, sorry, I'm probably throwing him a prayer.
I mean, you know, we've mentioned that in prayer before, but this is a bit of a prayer ball.
But it's okay, we're just going to roll with him.
He needs to go get his guitar, let's pray.
While he's doing that, I'm going to invite everybody here to stand.
Please stand. Let's stretch your legs for a second.
Before we come to the table for community.
And this is very important.
I don't want any of us who have been on a journey not had an opportunity to respond to the gospel.
It might not be you, it might be somebody next to you, it might be somebody who's been in the same church for a long time.
I've heard plenty of stories with people that went to church for a long time.
And it wasn't until they lived for 40 years that it was really the same for the answer.
So I'm going to ask, and I'm going to ask everybody to close your eyes.
And I'm not going to spend well with this, it's all good.
I'm going to pray, and I'm going to ask if there's a response from anyone in this room.
You need a response.
You don't have to do something embarrassing.
You don't have to even raise your hand.
You can look at me, that was before.
So that you know, because I would like to pray with you maybe,
or if somebody's in here to pray with you at this place.
I do, my wife and I do enjoy praying for people because we know that that's where a conversion comes together.
Father, in Jesus' name.
For today, a canvas student of each church, your gospel is the most important thing in our life.
And Jesus, if you have revealed yourself, even in the announcements of pouring the things going on in the church,
you revealed yourself in our time of music.
You revealed yourself in the time of standing.
And so, Father, I ask in your name that if anybody in this room has never publicly confessed that Jesus is Lord,
I want you to respond.
Look at me.
Look up.
You don't have to do anything.
It's not embarrassing.
You might need to do anything else.